<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2005 - 2006

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
  "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<!--
  Author: Eric Van Dewoestine
  -->

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Creating your first java project.</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Eric Van Dewoestine" email="ervandew@yahoo.com"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section id="project_create">
      <title>Creating a project</title>
      <p>
        Now that everything is installed and eclimd is up and running, you can
        create your first project.
      </p>
      <p>
        To do so, simply open up a vim window and execute:
      </p>
      <source>
        :ProjectCreate /path/to/my/project
      </source>
      <p>
        The path supplied will be the path to the root of your project.  This
        path may or may not exist.  If it does not exist it will be created for
        you.  If the path does exist, it will be examined for any source
        directories or libraries (jar files) that should be included in the
        project's classpath.  In either case the end result will be the creation
        of a <code>.project</code> and <code>.classpath</code> file in the
        supplied directory.  At this time, the <code>.project</code> file is
        nothing that you need worry about maintaining as it is purely for
        eclipse.  The <code>.classpath</code> file on the other hand, is used
        to manage your project's dependencies, including dependencies on other
        projects, other libraries, and the location of your source directories.
        For more on maintaining this file see the
        <a href="../../vim/java/classpath.html">classpath docs</a>.
      </p>
      <p>
        Once you've created your project you can now use the
        <strong>:ProjectList</strong> to list the available projects and you
        should see your newly created one in the list.
      </p>
      <source>
        project - /path/to/my/project
      </source>
      <p>
        The <strong>:ProjectList</strong> result is in the form of
        <code>projectName - /project/root/path</code>.  When you create
        projects, the last path element will be used for the project name.  If
        that element contains any spaces, they will be converted to underscores.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="project_settings">
      <title>Editing project settings.</title>
      <p>
        After creating a project, the next thing you'll probably want to do is
        edit your project's settings.  To do this you can use the
        <strong>:ProjectSettings</strong> command.  If your current vim window's
        working directory is at or under the project's root directory then you
        can execute the <strong>:ProjectSettings</strong> with no arguments,
        otherwise you will need to supply the project name.
      </p>
      <source>
        :ProjectSettings projectName
      </source>
      <p>
        After your first time editing your project's settings, a .settings
        directory will be created in the project's root directory.  In there are
        the project's preferences files.  You should avoid editing these files
        directly and stick to using <strong>:ProjectSettings</strong> to update
        them.
      </p>
      <note>
        If you have many projects and most of them share the same settings you
        can use the <strong>:Settings</strong> command instead to edit the
        global settings.  These global settings will apply to any project that
        has not overridden them with values via
        <strong>:ProjectSettings</strong>.
      </note>
    </section>
    <section id="next">
      <title>What's next</title>
      <p>
        Now that you have an eclim project, you can make full use of all the
        functionality provided.  You can continue to read the docs on this site
        for more information on what eclim is currently capabably of.
        You should probably start with learning how to maintian your
        <a href="../../vim/java/classpath.html">classpath</a> and then move on to
        learning all the <a href="../../vim/index.html#java">java functionality</a>
        that is available.
      </p>
      <p>
        Be sure to report any and all issues, comments, and suggestions.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
