<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2005 - 2008

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
  "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<!--
 Author: Eric Van Dewoestine
-->

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Contributing to Eclim</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Eric Van Dewoestine" email="ervandew@gmail.com"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>
      Eclim is a project developed entirely in my spare time, so its growth and
      success can be directly impacted by contributions from the community.
      There are several ways in which you can contribute:
    </p>
    <ol>
      <li>
        <strong>Documentation</strong>: The documentation can always use
        improvements.  Right now it is written entirely by me, and as such, it
        may not be as detailed in some areas as it should.  What the
        documentation could really use is some help from its users:
        <ul>
          <li>
            Point out any grammar or spelling errors, since some always manage
            to slip through.
          </li>
          <li>
            Point out areas of the documentation that are vague and could use
            elaboration.
          </li>
          <li>
            Write new guides to be included in the "Guides" section of the site.
          </li>
          <li>
            Write translations.  Eclim gets visitors from all over the world and
            it would be nice to be able to provide localized documentation for
            them.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>
        <strong>Bug Reports</strong>: Some people are a bit shy about speaking
        up and reporting bugs.  I want to urge people not to be.  If something
        doesn't work, report it.  It may be a bug, but even if it is just a
        configuration issue on your end, a misconception on how you thought it
        should work, or some other quirk specific to your environment, speak up.
        These can signal that some scripts may need to validate or account for
        some aspect of the user's environment, or that the documentation may
        need some work to ensure the user knows what to expect.  Any issue that
        goes unreported, goes unfixed, so please report all issues, big and
        small.
      </li>
      <li>
        <strong>Feature Requests</strong>: On occasion I receive a request or
        two, but I would like to encourage more people to voice their opinion on
        what they think should be added or changed in eclim.  Once again,
        nothing is too small to suggest.  Chances are, that if you have
        something that you would like added or changed, there are others out
        there that would benefit from the same addition or
        modification.<br/>
        To see what features I have already thought about, you can view the
        online <a href="todo.html">todo list</a>, and
        <a href="http://eclim.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/eclim/trunk/notes.txt?view=log">
          my secondary list
        </a>.
      </li>
      <li>
        <strong>Code Contributions</strong>: In addition to reporting bugs or
        requesting features, you can also take that next step and implement a
        fix or feature yourself.  I just ask that you document your patch
        accordingly so that I know exactly what you are attempting to fix or
        add.  Also, if you plan to add a medium or large feature, please let me
        know prior to beginning your work.  That way I can keep a small list of
        who is working on what to avoid any duplication of effort and link
        people together that wish to work on the same feature.  The list would
        also afford me the ability to contact you should a change to eclim
        possibly affect what you are working on.
        <!--br/><br/>
        It is probably worth mentioning a few things about being granted cvs
        commit privileges.  For now I would like all code committed to cvs to go
        through me so that I can provide a certain level of quality assurance.
        It is ultimately my responsibility to maintain the code in cvs, so I
        want to ensure that all code committed is maintainable. Should I be
        unable to contact you for whatever reason, I want to be able to quickly
        and effectively provide any fixes to the code you provided.  I also need
        to ensure that there are suitable test cases for your code so that I can
        maintain a set of regression tests to further maintain the code quality.
        -->
      </li>
      <!--li>
        <strong>Plugins</strong>: Eclim is currently broken up into several
        eclipse plugins, each targeting a specific area.  For instance, there is
        a plugin for java development (org.eclim.jdt), one for working with ant
        (org.eclim.ant), and another for working with maven (org.eclim.maven).
        <br/><br/>
        When viewing the <a href="todo.html">todo list</a>, you will notice that
        some of the features I would like added depend on third party plugins.
        These are great places to start development of new eclim plugins.  For
        instance, to add enhanced support for the springframework, it would make
        sense to integrate with the Spring IDE which is a

        My long term intension for eclim is to not only be a great java
        development tool, but also a
      </li-->
      <li>
        <strong>Monetary Contributions</strong>: I am not currently accepting any
        donations.  My day job pays well, and I work on eclim for the love
        of it.  If you have money you would like to donate, it would go to much
        better use if you donated to
        <a href="http://www.vim.org/sponsor/index.php">vim</a>, where it is used
        to help children in Uganda.  Feel free to mention your referral from
        eclim if appropriate.
      </li>
    </ol>
  </body>
</document>
